<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Londons looking backe to Ierusalem, or, Gods iudgements vpon others, are to be obserued by vs</title>
            <author>Jones, John, minister at St. Michael Basenshaw, London.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14722</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119135</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854342</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854342</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19758</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04605)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19758)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1549:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Londons looking backe to Ierusalem, or, Gods iudgements vpon others, are to be obserued by vs</title>
                  <author>Jones, John, minister at St. Michael Basenshaw, London.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [5], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones dwelling in Red-crosse-streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Will. Iones.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Gods iudgements upon others, are to be observed by us.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Peterborough Cathedral Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19758:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19758:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LONDONS LOOKING BACKE TO IERVSALEM, OR, GODS IVDGEMENTS VPON OTHERS, ARE TO BE OBSERVED BY VS.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Jeremiah. <hi>44.2.3.</hi> verſ.</bibl>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſtes, the God of Iſraël: Yee have ſeene all the evill, that I have brought upon Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, and upon all the Cities of Iudah: and behold this day, they are deſolate, and no man dwelleth therein.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Becauſe of the wickednes which they have committed, to provoke me to anger, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 7. 1630.</p>
            <p>Preached at Pauls Croſſe by IOHN IONES M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of Arts, Curate and Lecturer; at S. Michaels Baſenſhaw.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by WILLIAM IONES dwelling in Red-croſſe-ſtreete, 1633.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19758:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19758:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT, HONORABLE SIR NICOLAS RAYNTON, KNIGHT, LORD MAIOR of the Citie of LONDON. <hi>Together with the Right Worſhipfull his brethren, the Sheriffes, and Aldermen of the ſame Citty.</hi> 
            </head>
            <head type="sub">W. I. deſireth all bleſſings ſpirituall, and temporall to be powred upon you in this life, and eternall bleſſedneſſe in the life to come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>IGHT Honorable</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>And Right worſhipfull, I am bould to preſent unto you this Sermon, preached at Pauls Croſſe, becauſe the Authour had ſo intended, after that the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of ſome Chriſtian friends had prevailed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19758:3"/>
with him to have it publiſhed; which Sermon, is intituled <hi>Londons looking back to Ieruſalem,</hi> according as God ſend <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to looke to Shilo, what he did unto it, for the wickednes that was in it,</hi> which was his text handled: And what the ſinnes of Ieruſalem were this ſermon doth plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely diſcover, as pride, fulnes of bread, &amp; idlnes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Gods Ordinances and miniſtery; And hereby we may be admoniſhed of that generall out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward formality in Religion; but where is the life and power, in a holy walking with God? where is the earneſt contending for the faith once given unto the Saints?</p>
            <p>God hath advanced your Honour to this place of dignity: ſtand faſt, to that charge, which God and his Maieſtie hath put into your hands, to cut off the cords of all prophaneſſes, and Sabbath brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, &amp;c. And the Lord make you zealous for his glory; to ſtand faſt in that liberty: wherein Chriſt hath ſett you free. Receive this Right Honorable, and Right Worſhipfull, as a teſtimony of his, for your loues to Gods Church, in maintaining ſo many Preachers at home, and abroad, which drawes the great bleſsing of God upon you, and the Cittie for the ſame (as it was his ſpeech on his death bed) receive
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19758:3"/>
it Right Honorable, and Right worſhipfull Company of Haberdaſhers, from whom he received ſome yearely ſtipend while he lived, his Lectureſhip being but ſmale; Reade it Right Honorable, and Right worſhipfull; and the Lord writ it in the tables of every one of your hearts, that you may avoid the iudgements of the wicked, and inioy the bleſsings prepared for the righteous, &amp; that for the Lord Ieſus Chriſt his ſake: to whom be given all honor and glory, now, and for evermore. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours, and Worſhips daily Orator, WILL. IONES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="Psalm">
            <pb facs="tcp:19758:4"/>
            <head>This Pſalme, CXiX. The ſixt part, he gave to be ſung before his Sermon.</head>
            <lg n="41">
               <head>41</head>
               <l>THy mercyes great and manifolde,</l>
               <l>let me obtaine (O Lord:)</l>
               <l>Thy ſaving health let me enioy,</l>
               <l>according to thy word.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="42" type="verse">
               <l>So ſhall I ſtop the ſlanderous mouthes,</l>
               <l>of lewd men and uniuſt:</l>
               <l>For in thy faithfull promiſes,</l>
               <l>ſtandes my comfort and trust.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="43" type="verse">
               <l>The word of truth within my mouth,</l>
               <l>let ever ſtill be preſt:</l>
               <l>For in thy judgementes wonderfull,</l>
               <l>my hope doth ſtand and reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="44" type="verse">
               <l>And whilſt that breath within my breaſt,</l>
               <l>doth naturall life preſerue:</l>
               <l>Yea till this world ſhall be deſſolude,</l>
               <l>thy lawes will I obſerue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="45" type="verse">
               <l>So walke will I as ſet at large,</l>
               <l>and made free from all dread:</l>
               <l>Becauſe I ſought how for to keepe,</l>
               <l>thy preceptes and thy reede.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="46" type="verse">
               <l>Thy noble acts I will deſcribe,</l>
               <l>as things of moſt great fame:</l>
               <l>Even before Kings I will them blaſe,</l>
               <l>and ſhrinke no whit for ſhame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="47" type="verse">
               <l>I will reioyce then to obey,</l>
               <l>thy worthy heſtes and will:</l>
               <l>Which evermore I have loved beſt,</l>
               <l>and ſo will love them ſtill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="48" type="verse">
               <l>My hands will I lift to thy lawes,</l>
               <l>which <hi>I</hi> have dearely ſought:</l>
               <l>And practiſe thy commandements,</l>
               <l>in will, in deed, and thought.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19758:4"/>
            <head>Maſter Iones his Prayer before his Sermon.</head>
            <p>MOſt great and glorious Lord God, who by thy Almighty power haſt created the Heaven and the Earth, and by thy unſearchable wiſdome gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and guideſt the ſame: we vile and baſe wretches, that have defiled the Heavens by our ſinnes, and curſed the earth by our tranſgreſſions, doe proſtrate our ſelves in all humility before the throne of thy Divine Majeſty: beſeeching thee to looke upon us not in juſtice, but in mercy; not as we are in our ſelves, but in the face and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance of thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſt. In our ſelves we are altogether unworthy to come into thy holy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, to tread upon holy ground, or to meddle with holy things. This day is holy, ſet apart by thine owne ſelfe for thine owne holy worſhip: this place is holy, it is thy owne ſanctuary, thy ordinances are holy, &amp; the ſervice in which we are imployed, is a holy ſervice. But we are moſt vnholy, impure in our very beginnings, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure in our proceedings; all over polluted with ſinne: in all the faculties of our ſoules, in all the members of our bodies: in the notions &amp; imaginations of our minds, in the motions &amp; inclinations of our wils, in the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and deſires of our hearts, in the words of our mouthes, in the workes of our handes: wee are poore, and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and blinde, and naked, high-minded, vaine-min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, worldly-minded, falſe-hearted, full of hypocriſie, full of ſecurity, full of infidelity, wanting in charity, wanting in knowledge, in zeale, intemperance, in patience; deficient in all grace, abundant in all ſinne, wee have ſinned againſt all the meanes of grace: thy word, thy Sacraments, thy Sabbaths, thy Chriſt, thy Spirit; we have ſinned againſt all the times of grace: we have ſinned in the times of our childhood, in the times of
<pb facs="tcp:19758:5"/>
our youth, and our riper yeares not onely in the times of ignorance, but ſince wee have knowne thy will: not onely through infirmity, but preſumptuouſly: we have ſinned againſt all thy attributes, we have abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thy patience, provoked thy anger: we have ſinned againſt thy Iudgements, which ſhould have enforced us to obedience; againſt thy mercies, which ſhould haue allured us and led us to repentance: wee haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt all thy creatures, againſt heaven, and againſt earth: againſt all thy workes; againſt the worke of creation, by defacing thy Image; againſt the worke of thy preſeruation, by diſtruſting thy prouidence: againſt the worke of redemption, by our infidelity; againſt thy law, which is the rule of righteouſnes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Goſpell of grace and ſaluation; againſt our vow made unto thee in our baptiſme: we haue broken the firſt vow that ever we made, and never ſince haue beene faithfull in our promiſes unto thee: againſt our owne purpoſes and promiſes made unto thee in our prayers, and that before our calling, and ſince our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: in our generall calling, and in our particuler cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings: we haue failed and ſinned ſince it hath pleaſed thee of thy free mercy to tranſlate us out of the powers of darkneſſe into the kingdom of thy deare Sonne. What ſhall wee doe that haue thus ſinned againſt thee, ô thou preſeruer of men? whither ſhall we goe from thy ſpirit, or whither ſhall we ſly from thy preſence? If we aſcend up into heaven, thou art there: if we make our bed in the deepe, thou art there: if wee take the wings of the morning, and dwell in the uttermoſt parts of the ſea, even there ſhall thy hand finde us. No darkeneſſe can cover us from thy all-ſeeing eye, no place can ſhelter us from thy almighty hand: thy judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments can follow us, and thy vengeance take hold on us whitherſoever we goe. What then ſhall we doe in this perplexity? In all humility wee caſt downe our ſelves before the throne of thy mercy, bewailing our
<pb facs="tcp:19758:5"/>
miſery, with bleeding hearts and throbbing ſoules de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring our miſery, imploring thy mercy, condemning our ſelues, confeſſing our ſins; promiſing, purpoſing and reſoluing with all our hearts to forſake our ſinnes. Though we are out of meaſure ſinfull, yet thou art out of meaſure mercifull: thou art infinite in mercy, and with thee is plenteous redemption. The greater our ſins are, the greater ſhall be the glory of thy mercy, and of thy Sons merits, in forgiving our ſinnes, which are ſo many and ſo great. Pardon therefore, we pray thee, all our ſins paſt: waſh us from them in the pure la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of thy Sons blood. It is not the river <hi>Iordan,</hi> nor all the rivers of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> that can cleanſe us from our ſpirituall leproſie: onely thy Son, thine onely Sonne, and that pure fountaine of thy Sonnes blood, which thou haſt opened to the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> and to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> for ſin, and for uncleanneſſe. In that blood we beſeech thee to waſh us from our ſins, from the guilt of ſin, from the puniſhment of ſin, from the power of ſin, with that blood purge our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences from dead workes, and quicken us by thy Spirit unto a new life, that we may ſerve thee the true and ever-living God, zealouſly without feare, univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally without partiality, ſincerely without hypocriſie, conſtantly without apoſtacy, in all righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe all the dayes of our liues: that the end of our life may be the end of our faith, which is the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſoules. And although we are unworthy to pray for our ſelues, yet in the name of thy Sonne we are bold to enlarge our prayers for thy whole Church, howſoeuer diſtreſſed or wherſoever diſperſed through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the parts of the whole earth. Give thy Goſpell a free paſſage, repaire the ruines of <hi>Sion,</hi> build up the broken walles of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and with the breath of thy noſtrills blow downe the walls of Iericho. In thy due time put an end to the troubles of the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. Why withdraweſt thou thy hand, even thy
<pb facs="tcp:19758:6"/>
right hand; and doeſt not plucke it out of thy boſome? how long oh Lord, how long wilt thou ſuffer the blood of thy ſeruants to be ſpilt upon the ground? Thou that didſt once heare and regard the blood of <hi>Abel,</hi> one man crying for vengeance; wilt thou not heare the blood of many thouſands? What advantage canſt thou have in giving over thy owne children to the fury of their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? ſhall thy enemies triumph, and thy children pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh? ſhall thy enimies reioyce &amp; thy children mourne? ſhall the light of thy Goſpell be eclipſed, the ſplendour of thy glory obſcured, thy temple defiled, thy name diſhonoured, thy truth ſlandered? Are they of Babilon better than they of Sion? or is there any other people that knoweth thee beſides Iſrael? or what generation hath ſo beleeued thy couenant as <hi>Iacob?</hi> Ariſe then oh Lord, ariſe, plead thy owne cauſe, honour thy owne name, defend thy owne altar, fight thy owne battaile, protect thy owne people: behold the pride of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and ſend thy wrath upon their heads: throw downe the forces of all them that haue purpoſed cruel things againſt thy Sanctuary, againſt the top of Sion, thy hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed houſe, the place where thine honour dwelleth. Make every nation to acknowledge that thou art the God of all power, that there is none other that protects thy Church and truth but thou onely. Protect thy Church and truth among us, and all that thou haſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in authority over us; eſpecially his ſacred Maieſty, <hi>Charles,</hi> by thy gracious providence King of great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, France and Ireland defender of the true, ancient, Catholick Apoſtolick faith, and in all cauſes, and over all perſons, as well Eccleſiaſticall as civill, next under thee and thy Sonne Chriſt, ſupreme governour. Bleſſe we beſeech thee his royall conſort Queene <hi>Mary:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching thee that with Mary ſhee may chuſe the better thing that cannot be taken from her. Bleſſe the preſent pledges of our ſucceeeding hopes, Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> with lady <hi>Mary</hi> his ſiſter. O Lord grant that as they grow in
<pb facs="tcp:19758:6"/>
yeares, ſo they may grow in grace and favour with thee and with men. Bleſſe the reſt of the Royall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genie beyond the ſcaes, the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> with her princely iſſue, when thou ſeemeſt beſt, ſettle them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, in their former inheritance, that they may be nurſing Fathers and mothers unto thy Church. Bleſſe the Right Honorable the privie Councel, the true hearted Nobility and Gentrie of our Land, the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Iudges, all vnto whom thou haſt committed the ſword of iuſtice, all Miniſters vnto whom thou haſt committed the ſword of the ſpirit, what names or titles ſoever diſtinguiſhed; whether Archbiſhops Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, or inferiour Paſtors. And that there may be a continuall ſupply of able men to governe both in Church and common wealth, bleſſe all nurſeries of good learning, eſpecially the two famous Vniverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this Land, Cambridge and Oxford, water the young plants that are in both of them, with the dew of thy grace that they may grow vp as Cedars in Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon for the building of Sion. And comfort all that are comfortleſſe oh thou Father of comfort, and God of all conſolation, viſite the ſicke, ſtrengthen the weake, heale the wounded, bind vp the broken hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, gather the diſperſed redeeme them that are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralled, releeue them that are impoveriſhed, ſuccour them that are tempted, reſtore them that are fallen by infirmitie, and eſtabliſh them that ſtand by thy free ſpirit. Finally, giue a bleſſing we pray thee, to this our meeting, in this thy houſe vpon this thy day: to ſpeake and to heare thy holy word, O Lord God I am a child, and cannot ſpeake, I am of polluted lipes, and ſlow of ſpeech, but thou art he that canſt giue ſight to the blind, and ſpeech to the dumbe, therefore untie the ſtrings of my ſtamering tongue, and touch it with a coale from thine alter, my doctrine ſhall drop as doth the raine and as the dew vpon the graſſe. And for this thy people, touch their eares and their hearts
<pb facs="tcp:19758:7"/>
with the finger of thy bleſſed ſpirit that they may heare thy word attentiuely, conceiue it rightly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it readily, apply it wiſely; treaſure it upon their memories, faithfully practiſe it, in their life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations conſcionably ſo all our vnderſtandings may be enlightned, our hearts purified, our conſcience ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, our ſinfull liues reformed and our ſoules ſaved yea, the whole man at length glorified in the land of the living. And that in and through thy deare ſoone, our onely Saviour Ieſus Chriſt, in whoſe name and words, we pray: Our Father &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19758:7"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IEREMIE 7.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But go yee now unto my place which was in Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loh; where I ſet my name at the firſt: and ſee what I did unto it for the wickedneſſe of my people Jſrael.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>VCH is the lenity and long animi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Almighty God, that before he proceedes to the puniſhment of ſinners hee gives them many war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; before he ſends the ſtorme ſhall not now profit you that are wicked, but you and your temple ſhall be deſtroyed. The temple is not more excellent than another place; but for the Arke and the Alter: indeed it is ſomewhat more adorned, but all the excellency and ſanctity lie in them. And were not theſe as well in <hi>Shiloh?</hi> yet notwithſtanding it was ruinated. So that it is but a folly in you to wax proud of theſe things, as if their ſanctity without your ſanctity could ſave you from the wrath to come. Therefore, for the abating of your pride and the rectifying of of your confidence, <hi>Go ye to my place &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which text, though at firſt ſight, ſeemes not
<pb facs="tcp:19758:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19758:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19758:9"/>
ſhoot. Yea, he doth often ſhew us his bow, but takes neither ſtring, nor ſhaft into his hand. <hi>Thou haſt ſhewed the people hard things, Pſal.</hi> 60.3. Shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not impoſed: he ſhewes his bow, before hee ſhootes; and his rod, before he layes it on. So true is that ſpeech of the Church, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.33. <hi>The Lord doth not afflict willingly, nor grieve the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men.</hi> Search the rolles of holy writ, and there yee ſhall obſerve him, ſometimes grieving for ſinne, ſometimes complaining of it, ſomtimes threatning of it, ſometime propoſing to us the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of his iudgements upon others for ſuch and ſuch ſinnes: as here to Ieruſalem, that ſhee might ſee her miſerable condition &amp; fall to ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy deprecation, to her and her inhabitants, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth <hi>Shiloh,</hi> as a ſpectacle of his juſtice, and that for thoſe ſinnes of which <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was as deepely guilty as ever <hi>Shiloh</hi> was. <hi>Ite ad locum meum in Silo, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ paragraphs">
                  <desc>〈1… paragraphs〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19758:9"/>
chuſe but ſet a ſudden ſtop and period to their proſperity: yet did they truſt for ſafety in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward badges of their religion, and eſpecially in their Temple, ſaying, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> The temple of the Lord is holy &amp; glorious &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced of all: how is it poſſible that any ſhould deſtroy the temple of the Lord, or vanquiſh the citty in which that temple is? Oh, ſaith <hi>Ieremie, truſt yee not in ſuch lying words:</hi> for the holines of the place doth little availe a people, if they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves be not holy in their lives. For proofe of which goe but unto <hi>Shiloh:</hi> the holineſſe of the place in <hi>Shiloh</hi> (where at firſt the holy Tabernacle ſtaid for a long time, &amp; the Ark before which the name of God was invocated, and the worſhip of ſacrifices adminiſtred) did nothing profit the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they gave themſelves to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, but together with them that place was reiected of the Lord: ſo the temple of <hi>Salomon</hi> ſhall not now profit you that are wicked, but you and your temple ſhall be deſtroyed. The temple is not more excellent than another place; but for the Arke and the Alter: indeed it is ſomewhat more adorned, but all the excellency and ſanctity lie in them. And were not theſe as well in <hi>Shiloh?</hi> yet notwithſtanding it was ruinated. So that it is but a folly in you to wax proud of theſe things, as if their ſanctity without your ſanctity could ſave you from the wrath to come. Therefore, for the abating of your pride and the rectifying of of your confidence, <hi>Go ye to my place &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which text, though at firſt ſight, ſeemes not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19758:10"/>
to meddle with matters preſent now, of neere home, but paſt and farre off, matters of another Meridian, aloofe from us as farre as <hi>Shiloh,</hi> or <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem;</hi> concerning not Chriſtians, but Iewes, mentioning not our wickedneſſe but theirs, <hi>the wickedneſſe of the People Iſrael:</hi> Yet as the Sunne, though it riſe in the Eaſt, ſets in the Weſt, by that time the Text hath gone its circuit, it may come to ſet farre from where it roſe: as <hi>Nathan</hi> though he began with a parrable of two men and a ſheep, yet brought it about in the end to, <hi>Thou art the man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In our Text there is a journey preſcribed, yea a double journey, the one corporall, <hi>Go;</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects the body: the other ſpirituall, <hi>ſee;</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects the minde. Or if you like it better, here is a direction to a double action, <hi>Go and ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Ite, go yee:</hi> and that is amplified by two cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, the time and the place: beſides which yee may adde the conſideration of the perſons, <hi>Yee, Go yee.</hi> And 1. the perſons are the inhabitants of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> 2. the time is <hi>now,</hi> go preſently, for delay breeds danger. And 3. for the place it hath a double deſcription:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Nominall, it is <hi>Shiloh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Reall, it is the place where <hi>God did ſet his name at the first.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 What that place was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſively.</note>In which latter are diverſe particulars to bee obſerved. 1. proprietary or owner of it, God; <hi>my place,</hi> ſaith the Lord; which ſhewes the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of it: for that muſt needs be glorious which is the place of God,<note place="margin">1 King. 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>the King of glory,</hi> But the whole
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19758:10"/>
world is Gods as well as <hi>Shiloh</hi> was: true, but this is his in ſpeciall reſpects, ſet down in the next paſſage, expreſſing the reaſon, why <hi>Shiloh</hi> was ſo glorious. it was a priveledged place, for 1. <hi>God did ſet his name there:</hi> and not onely ſo, but 2.<note place="margin">2 What that place was poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively.</note> he ſet it there <hi>at the firſt.</hi> Ther's the glory of the place, the ſanctity and previledge of the place, and the antiquity of each. <hi>Go yee now &amp;c.</hi> ther's the firſt act.</p>
            <p>The ſecond followeth, <hi>Videte, See:</hi> not onely <hi>Go,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.46.</note> but <hi>Go and ſee,</hi> as <hi>Philip</hi> to <hi>Nathaniell, Come and ſee:</hi> When yee are come to <hi>Shiloh,</hi> bee not idle there, but open your eyes and ſee, imploy your mindes and conſider, <hi>What I did unto it for the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Obſerve what was done unto it, the calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that befell it:</p>
            <p n="2">2. Who was the Authour of that calamity, <hi>I,</hi> ſaith the Lord:</p>
            <p n="3">3. What was the impulſive cauſe that provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the Lord to inflict that calamity, <hi>Wickedneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Whoſe wickedneſſe it was that could ſo farre provoke him as to reiect his owne place <hi>Shiloh,</hi> the wickedneſſe of his owne people <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Where wickedneſſe raigneth, God will not ſpare that place, though it be <hi>Shiloh,</hi> nor that people though it be <hi>Iſrael, Go yee now &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will handle the text two wayes. Firſt, Exege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically or Paraphraſtically, by way of explicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: then Diadactically or Doctrinally, by way of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. And I begin with the firſt act, <hi>Ite, Go yee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19758:11"/>Men for the moſt part are like the ſnaile, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes carrying her houſe on her backe. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly we love a ſedentary life, and are loath to leave our cuſhion, unwilling to diſeaſe our ſelves, <hi>Vtinam hoc eſſet laborare,</hi> ſaid he that lay along and ſtretcht himſelf. As the ſlothful man is <hi>Socors,</hi> that is, <hi>Sine corde,</hi> without a heart; wanting affection and courage to doe what he knowes: ſo is he <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> that is <hi>Pede aeger;</hi> he lackes a foote to convey him to any honeſt imployment. Like thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ones overwhelmed in the generall deluge, he can ſit ſtill, and laugh and ſing, till the water ſtop his wind and he be drowned. But wiſdome is not gotten by ſitting at home in <hi>Hemicyclo,</hi> in an halfe mooned chaire, or by lurking in a corner: as <hi>Solon Socrates, Caeſar, Plato, Cicero,</hi> &amp; other Pagans knew well, who, to purchaſe wiſdome, expoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the tempeſts of forraigne climates. And God himſelfe, that they might learne wiſedome, doth here ſend the <hi>Iewes</hi> out of their own Citty. <hi>Ite, Go yee.</hi> So long as you containe your ſelves within the narrow compaſſe of your domeſticall ſeate, like ſheepe in a pinfold, yee ſtand gazing upon the beauty of your city, the outward ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of your temple, and admiring at thoſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gifts, with which it is inriched, not admitting the leaſt thought of a change. Let me therefore councell you no longer to ſhroud your ſelves in your city, but meaſure a few ſteps, <hi>Go</hi> out of your owne place and take notice how things paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, <hi>Goe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And <hi>Go yee; yee</hi> the inhabitants of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19758:11"/>
yee that ſtand ſo much upon your outward pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives, that looke for ſafety in my ſanctuary, be your ſinnes never ſo many. Yee are the fitteſt ſchollers to take out that leſſon which I am about to teach, but out of your owne ſchoole. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Go yee, Yee</hi> that ſleepe in the chaire of ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſuppoſing there is nothing good but that which yee know, no houſe comodious but your owne, no aire to live in but where yee breath, no life like that which yee leade in darkneſſe and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, <hi>Go yee.</hi> Go from your chaire or bed, where yee ſleepe in ſecurity; go from your ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall pleaſures, bewitching paſtimes, brutiſh pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, beaſtly companions; <hi>Go</hi> from your cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie coldneſſe and ſtupiditie, <hi>Go</hi> from your ſelf-conceited oppinions and imaginations, it is to you that are ſecure that I doe here direct my ſpeech, lifting up my voice like a trumpet, &amp; row ſing you up from that ſleeping ſtoole of yours. Therefore <hi>Go yee, yee</hi> your ſelves perſonally, ſtand not to the report of others, but <hi>go</hi> your ſelves unto the place, and ſee with your owne eyes <hi>What I did unto it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And <hi>Go now</hi> too: make no delay, <hi>Now</hi> is the onely ſure part of our time, that which is paſt, is come and gone: that which is to come may peradventure never come. Till to morrow, till this evening, till an houre hence wee have no aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance. <hi>Now</hi> therefore; or, if not <hi>Now,</hi> as neere <hi>Now,</hi> with as little diſtance from it as may be, <hi>Go yee to my place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>My place,</hi> that the next, be not extravagant,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19758:12"/>
ſtraggle not to thoſe places to which your owne luſts invite you, that is to follow <hi>Iudas,</hi> who went to <hi>his own place:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 1.</note> go not on neither in the way that ye have begun but go whether I direct you; <hi>ad locum meum, to my place;</hi> to go thither will bee worth your labour indeed. So that this licenſe of travell is limited and bounded, as you ſee. Some there are that love travel as their life, ſo they may be gadding, they care not to what place it bee: they dare breath in the poyſonous ayre of <hi>Italy,</hi> and touch the very pommell of the <hi>Chaire of peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence:</hi> So the Devill playes the Marſhall and takes them up, becauſe they ſtraggle abroad without a warrant or paſport. We can never have comfort in any travell or journey, except it be ſo bounded as this in our text. <hi>Go yee,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>ad lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum meum, to my place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>My place which was: was,</hi> and is not: God ſometimes calles them his people which were not his people;<note place="margin">Rom. 9.25.</note> and that his place which was not his place: and on the otherſide ſometime they which were his people ceaſe to be his people, and that which was his place ceaſeth to be his place. <hi>My place which was: was,</hi> and is not.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Was at Shiloh:</hi> thats the next, God ſends them not out of their own coaſts into a forraigne country, as he did <hi>Abraham,</hi> nor yet to a remote place in their owne country; <hi>Go,</hi> ſaith he, to <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loh,</hi> thats not farre, yee have the name of the place and cannot miſſe it, nay, ye cannot but know it, it being but ſix miles diſtant from your Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:19758:12"/>This <hi>Shiloh</hi> was once <hi>my place,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 12.5, 6.</note> that which I choſe for my ſelfe, above all other places. For the underſtanding of which reade, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 18.1. There yee ſhall find that after the <hi>Cananites</hi> were ſubdued unto the <hi>Iſraellites,</hi> and a place to bee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, where the people might meet for divine ſervice, God put it into their hearts to make choice of <hi>Shiloh.</hi> 1. Becauſe of the beauty and glory of it, <hi>Ioſephus,</hi> ſpeaking of this matter, ſaith:<note place="margin">Lib. 5. c. 1. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit.</note> they placed the ſacred Tabernacle in the Citty of <hi>Shiloh,</hi> and ſets downe this as the reaſon of; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. For it ſeemed to be a meet place by reaſon of the beauty of the ſame, where the Arke might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, till ſuch time as their affaires of State per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them to build a Temple. Secondly, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the convenience of it for the whole peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to meet there, being ſcituate aboute the midſt of the land of promiſe, as I ſaid not aboue ſixe miles diſtant from <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 5.5.</note> which was even in the midſt, the navell of the land, as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> termes it<note n="*" place="margin">To which ſome apply that text. Ezek. 38.12.</note>. Thirdly, becauſe it did belong to <hi>Ephraim,</hi> which was more warlike then the other tribes,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 78.9.</note> and ſo more able to defend the place of Gods worſhippe. Fourthly, principally, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their captaine <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> was of<note n="b" place="margin">Ioſh. 19.49, 50, 51. &amp; Num. 13.8.</note> 
               <hi>Ephraim,</hi> he who aſſembled them to determine of the place: and where hee dwelt and had decreed their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne meetings, there they perſwaded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon good ground, that the obſervation of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19758:13"/>
the Law and ſacred rites would bee more exact. For theſe reaſons, and eſpecially by the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God, who had made choice of that place, they ſet up the Tabernacle of the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at <hi>Shiloh,</hi> appointed that as a fixed ſeat for the Tabernacle, which before had beene in continuall motion; and for the Arke which was within it, that all the <hi>Iewes</hi> might repaire unto it in their chiefe ſolemnities, being to worſhip God with the oblation of their Sacrifices and firſt fruits, as wee reade of <hi>Elkanah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.3. <hi>He went up out of his City yearely, to worſhip and to Sacrifice unto the Lord in Shiloh.</hi> In this reſpect <hi>Shiloh</hi> was the place of God, <hi>my place,</hi> ſaith the Lord, the place where <hi>I did ſet my name,</hi> that is,<note n="*" place="margin">Calvin in loc.</note> 
               <hi>Vbi volui arcam reſidere,</hi> where I made my Ark to dwell (for<note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 6.2.</note> the Arke is called by the <hi>name of God,</hi> and the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word imports a fixed reſidence:) <hi>my place,</hi> the place where I appointed my worſhip and the uſe of my ordinances, by which I am made knowne unto you, as a man is made knowne by his name. And which is yet more, I did not onely ſet my name there, but did ſet it there <hi>at the first, In prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipio,</hi> before your Temple was built, nay, before it was known that mount <hi>Sion</hi> ſhould be the place where I would have a Temple built, then was <hi>Shiloh my place,</hi> conſecrated to my ſervice. All this conſidered, Firſt, the propinquity of the place, it is <hi>Shiloh,</hi> and thats but ſix miles diſtant from your Citty: Secondly, the glory of the place, together with the ſanctity of it, that it is <hi>my place,</hi> that which I made choice of above all other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19758:13"/>
in the world, there to <hi>ſet my name,</hi> to ſettle my Ark &amp; Tabernacle &amp; divine worſhip. Thirdly, the antiquity of the place and priviledges of it, that I did <hi>ſet my name there at the first,</hi> long before the Temple of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was thought on; I ſay, all this conſidered, it will bee worth your labour to follow my councell in this, <hi>Goe yee now &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to goe thither, is not all, that were ſoone done; to an <hi>Ite</hi> you muſt adde a <hi>Videte, Go and ſee,</hi> as the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaid to his ſervants, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 7.14. Your feete, your ankles, your locomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive faculty, were given you to <hi>goe;</hi> the ſpheares of your eyes, theſe lights, this ſharpnes of ſight, were given you to <hi>ſee:</hi> you are neither lame, nor blinde, therefore <hi>Ite &amp; videte, Goe and ſee.</hi> The Philoſopher<note n="*" place="margin">Ariſt. lib. de ſenſu et ſenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to c. 2.</note> concludes againſt the Platoniſts, that the fight drawes moſt after the Element of water; for<note n="*" place="margin">Ariſt. de Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner &amp; Corrupt l. 2. c. 2.</note> as water is hardly kept within his owne, or without the limits of his neighbour E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements: ſo the ſight, denied by nature to ſee it ſelfe, is never ſatisfied<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 27.20.</note> with gazing upon other creatures, <hi>The eye is not ſatisfied with ſeeing, Eccleſ.</hi> 1.8.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a volubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatè <hi>Scapula</hi>
               </note> And there is not more volubillity<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 27.20.</note> in the eye, then curioſity in the minde, of man, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ſtrange and uncouth ſights. If ſuch obiects be neere, no lockes can hold us, <hi>we muſt out to ſee.</hi> Then what needs ſuch a precept as this in our Text, <hi>Ite &amp; videte, Goe and ſee?</hi> Yes: for it is not barely to ſee, to caſt their eyes where they liſt themſelves, but to fixe them upon that obiect to which God directs them. <hi>See,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>what I did unto Shiloh, for &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:19758:14"/>Marke the calamity which befell that place, which is in ſituation ſo neere you, in antiquity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond you, in glory and ſanctity ſometimes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to that Temple wherein yee truſt. The calamity of it is recorded. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. Where yee ſhall reade, that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> being ſmitten by the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> and in great diſtreſſe, they ſent for the Arke out of <hi>Shiloh,</hi> truſting that the Arke (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a pledge of Gods preſence and aſſiſtance) might then ſave them out of the hands of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, as if their ſinnes were not of force to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the power of God from the Arke, and to make a divorce between the truth and the figure. Well, the Arke is brought, and in it the Law writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in tables, but it had beene better if they had had the Law written in their hearts, when the Arke came into the campe, all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhouted with a great ſhout, ſo that the earth rang againe. Her's great joy, but to little purpoſe; they triumph be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the victory and without the victory; for they triumph without God,<note place="margin">Calvin. Hom. <hi>17.</hi> in lib <hi>1.</hi> Sam.</note> nay againſt God do they erect their trophees of triumph, not being reconciled unto him by faith and repentance. The vanity of their triumph may appeare by the iſſue of the battell: for at the preſence of the Arke they received a greater overthrow then before. The ſlaughter was very great, for there fell of <hi>Iſrael</hi> 3 0000. footemen, <hi>Their young men were conſumed and their Prieſts ſlaine:</hi> yea, <hi>the Arke</hi> it ſelfe, the pledge of Gods favour and ſuccour, <hi>the ſtrength and glory of Iſrael was taken</hi> by the enemies. And (as S. <hi>Ierome</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">apud Sanctiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Ier. 7.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sic etiam Pellican. ibid.</note> obſerves) the place, where <hi>Shiloh</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:19758:14"/>
was, is utterly ruinated and made deſolate. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, <hi>Shiloh</hi> forfeited her Charter, and loſt her former priviledges<note n="*" place="margin">Chriſtophor a Caſtro. ibid. 1 Sam. 7.1.</note> the reſidence of the Arke. For after the <hi>Philiſtimes</hi> had brought it to <hi>Bethſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſh,</hi> it was fetcht to <hi>Kiriath-jearim,</hi> and ſo carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from place to place, but never more to <hi>Shiloh;</hi> where it had continued from the dayes of <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> to the death of <hi>Eli,</hi> 369. yeares,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ghiſler</hi> in Ier. 7 12.</note> according to the Chronologie of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> or 351. according to the Computation of other Authors. This was the calamity which befell <hi>Shiloh,</hi> it ceaſed for ever to be the place of Gods worſhip: which came not to paſſe by chance, but by the Divine providence. <hi>See,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>what I did unto it.</hi> The <hi>Philistims</hi> were but my inſtruments in this worke; <hi>I,</hi> the chiefe Agent. <hi>Non vires ferri,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſon. Epigr. 5.</note> 
               <hi>ſed fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rientis agunt. I did it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet I did it not out of any hatred, but in my iuſtice; not becauſe I deſired their woe, but becauſe I was provoked by their ſinne, even <hi>the Wickedneſſe of my people Iſrael. My people,</hi> for ſo were they in <hi>Shiloh</hi> as well as you in <hi>Ieruſalem, My people,</hi> not onely as all by right of poſſeſſion, but as you by the right of confederation and the grace of acceptation. But ſuch is the righteouſnes of my nature, ſuch the purity, of mine eyes, that I cannot with approbation behold ſinne, no,<note place="margin">Amos 3.2.</note> not in mine owne people. If they, whome I have ſo much honored as to be <hi>my people,</hi> will ſo diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner me as to commit wickednes againſt me, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but glorifie my ſelfe by doing iuſtice upon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſider this ye that now profeſſe your
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19758:15"/>
ſelves to be my people, and glory ſo much in the beautie of your temple, <hi>Goe yee now &amp;c.</hi> Hitherto be it ſpoken of the words exegetically: I now come to handle them Doctrinally. And now taske your wits and your memories and keepe pace with me; for within the compaſſe of the time I ſhall runne over theſe five obſervations, all of them naturally deduced, not tyranouſly inforced from the words.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Where God doth ſet his name, thats the peculier place of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The holineſſe of the place cannot protect a people, except there be holineſſe in the perſons, who inhabit that place.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is God who inflicts iudgement upon a place or people. <hi>See,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>what I did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It is the wickedneſſe of a people which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokes him to judgement, <hi>I did it,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for the wickedneſſe of my people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The judgements of God inflicted upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are to be obſerved by us: eſpecially, if they be ſuch as light upon his owne place and people. And this is the maine point which the text drives at. For to this end doth the Lord ſend them of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> to ſchoole (as it were) unto <hi>Shiloh: Go ye now &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſerva.</hi> 8.1</note>1. Where God doth ſet his name, or place his worſhip and ordinances, that's the peculier place of God. <hi>My place,</hi> ſaith the Lord here; and <hi>My houſe, Ier.</hi> 11.15. <hi>thy houſe,</hi> ſaith the Saints<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 84.5. &amp; 42.4.</note>; his <hi>banqueting</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Cant. 2.4. Pſal. 11.4. &amp; 74.7. &amp; 26.8. 2 Chron. 6.41.</note> 
               <hi>houſe</hi> ſaith the Spouſe; <hi>his holy Temple,</hi> ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">Cant. 2.4. Pſal. 11.4. &amp; 74.7. &amp; 26.8. 2 Chron. 6.41.</note> 
               <hi>David, the dwelling place of his name,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19758:15"/>
the place where his honour dwelleth.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> For God that is preſent in every place, is more eſpecially preſent in that place; and God that doth protect us in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very place, doth more eſpecially protect us in that place; and God that gives bleſſings in every place, gives a more eſpecial bleſſing in that place. Firſt, I ſay, God, who is preſent in every place, is more eſpecially preſent in that place, where he doth <hi>ſet his name,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 6 4 1.</note> or ſettle his worſhip and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances: that's his <hi>dwelling place,</hi> and his <hi>reſting place.</hi> He is in every place, but doth <hi>not dwell or reſt</hi> in every place. <hi>The Lord is in his holy Temple, the Lords throne is in heaven, Pſal.</hi> 11.4. Hee is ſo in his <hi>Temple,</hi> as he is in <hi>heaven:</hi> that which <hi>heauen</hi> is above, is his <hi>Temple</hi> beneath, in <hi>heauen</hi> &amp; ſo in his <hi>Temple,</hi> he is preſent after a ſpeciall manner; in <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> is his glorious preſence, in his <hi>Temple</hi> on earth his gracious preſence; <hi>his</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 27.4.</note> 
               <hi>beauty,</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 40.34.</note> 
               <hi>his glory</hi> too in ſome ſort; <hi>his face and countenance. When ſhall I come &amp; appeare before God? Pſal.</hi> 42.2. <hi>Hebr. Before the face of God:</hi> for the <hi>face, countenance</hi> and ſpeciall preſence of God is in his <hi>holy Temple.</hi> When <hi>Caine</hi> departed from the family of <hi>Adam,</hi> which was then the onely place where God was worſhipped, it is ſaid <hi>he went out from the preſence of the Lord. Gen.</hi> 4.16. becauſe where he is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped, ther's his ſpeciall preſence, where Chriſt promiſeth in thoſe words, <hi>Where two or three are gathered together in my name, I will bee there in the midſt among them.</hi> There, how? not onely ſo as I am every where, but in a more ſingular manner; I will be there by the preſence of my grace and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19758:16"/>
aſſiſtance of my ſpirit. In the time of the Law God was worſhiped before the Arke, and the Ark was called by the name of the Lord, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.2. and when the Arke removed, they ſpake to it as to the Lord; <hi>Riſe up, Lord, and let thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies be ſcattered, Num</hi> 10.34. The reaſon was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Arke was a ſigne to the people of Gods preſence among them. So now are our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, wherein God is worſhipped.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As there is Gods gracious preſence, ſo there is his gracious Protection, and therefore the place where he is worſhipped, is his peculiar place. It is like thoſe Cities of refuge, which God appointed among the Iſraelites, whither he that had offended might fly for ſafety. The walls of <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple were carved round about with figures of Cherubims,<note place="margin">1 King. 6.29.</note> and palme trees, and open flowers within and without. The palme trees and flowers, did type out the Saints (that grow up like palme-trees in the houſe of God) together with the variety of their gifts: the Cherubims ſignified the Angels, by whoſe Miniſtery God protects his people, and that in a ſpeciall manner when they are in his houſe.<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.5. &amp; 91.1.</note> That is Gods pavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, wherin he hideth his children; the ſecret place and the ſhadow of the Almighty, that is, the defenſe (or as it is in the Greeke tranſlation) <hi>The protection of the Almighty when the incestuous perſon was cast out of the Church of Corinth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.5. 1 Tim. 1 20.</note> it is laid, he was delivered up to Satan,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Calvin.</hi> &amp; P. Matyr in 1 Cor. 5.5.</note> the like is ſpoken of <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Calvin.</hi> &amp; P. Matyr in 1 Cor. 5.5.</note>: to Satan, that is, to the tyrannie of Satan<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Calvin.</hi> &amp; P. Matyr in 1 Cor. 5.5.</note> to the power of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19758:16"/>
er of the evill Angells: they wanted the protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God and his good Angells, and ſo doe all thoſe that are excluded the Church. The firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was placed in Paradiſe that hee might dreſſe and keepe it: ſo (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Bern. In de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatione Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Ier. 6.</note>) is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Adam</hi> in his Church, which is a Paradiſe, or garden of delight, to defend and keepe it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Where God is worſhipped, ther's his ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall bleſſing, that attends his ordinances. Bleſſed are they that dwell in thy houſe, they goe from ſtrength to ſtrength,<note place="margin">So Pſal. 65.4.</note> the Lord will give them grace and glory: grace, by the meanes of grace here, and glory hereafter. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.4. &amp;c. When God promiſeth to give ſpeciall bleſſings, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to give them in his houſe and within his walls. <hi>Iſay.</hi> 56.5, 7. Contrariwiſe, when God threatens to withdraw his bleſſings from a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he excludes them his houſe.<note n="*" place="margin">Hoſ. 9.4.15</note> Now if Gods ſpeciall preſence, and ſpeciall protection, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall bleſſing be there, where hee is worſhipped, then that muſt needes bee the peculiar place of God.</p>
            <p>What terror ſhould this ſtrike to the hearts of thoſe, that offer any violence to this place,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> the peculiar place of God? Will a Prince ſuffer his pallace to be demoliſhed or battered? no more will God ſuffer any, without ſpeciall puniſhment, to wrong his Church, which is his pallace, his pavilion, his dwelling place, and his reſting place. <hi>If any man deſtroy the Temple of God, him will God deſtroy.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17. But who are they, that be cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable in this kind? Not onely open enemies that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19758:17"/>
by devaſtation lay it waſt, but alſo ſecret ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that undermine it, by Schiſmes and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Schiſmaticks, Such as as make rents in the Church, dividing themſelues from the vnitie of it, and ſcorning the authoritie of it, doe offer great violence to the peculiar place of God.<note place="margin">Nam prodito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res quidem ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, quicunque in hoc Domini caſtrum in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos eius intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducere moliun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quales ſunt vti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> detracto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res Deo odibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, qui diſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias ſeminant, nutriunt ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dala inter fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres. Sicut e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim in pace fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus eſt locus Domini, ſic in diſcordia locu diabolo fieri manifeſtum eſt &amp;c Bern. in de dicatione Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Ier. 3.</note> They betray it into the hands of the enemies, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Gods houſe, they make it <hi>ſpeluneam dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momorum,</hi> a denne of Divells, ſaith <hi>Bernard, Nil diſſociabile firmum est.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Prudent. Pſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chom. S. Bern. in de dicat. Eccleſ. Ier. 1.</note> 
               <hi>A Kingdome divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it ſelfe cannot ſtand.</hi> Stones of one building that jarre one with another, will ruine the whole houſe. <hi>Sola conjunctio facit domum</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ia. Ier. 2.</note>. It is vnion that makes a houſe: wood and ſtones diſvnited cannot doe it. Let thoſe violent and turbulent ſpirits conſider and thinke on this, by whome diviſion and diſcord is fomented in the houſe of God: they goe about to ruinate this houſe, and to drive God himſelfe away from it. For (as <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> noteth) he will not abide in ſuch a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome where there is diviſion, nor in ſuch a houſe which is neere to deſolation. To theſe factious ſpirits I propound for an example <hi>Corah</hi> and his accomplices, ſo ſeverely puniſhed for this ſinne: becauſe they had made a Schiſme in the Church, God made a Schiſme in the earth, the ground clave aſunder, the earth opened her mouth and ſwallowed them up. <hi>Num.</hi> 16.31.</p>
            <p>But not onely by Schiſme, by Sacriledge alſo is violence offered to the peculiar place of God: when the goods of the Church; things ſacred and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19758:17"/>
ſequeſtred from common uſe, are alienated and taken away by the felonious hands of ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous catchpolles. A ſinne too common amongſt us: the region of it being white, and ready for harveſt, and calling for a ſickle from heaven to cut it downe. As<note n="*" place="margin">Epiſt. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>no 1088. cited by D. Tilleſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in his Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions upon Selden.</note> 
               <hi>Ivo Carnotenſis</hi> once complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſo may every Godly man at this day: <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta inordinata video in domo Dei, quae me torquent; maxime quod apud nos, qui altari non ſerviunt, de al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari vivunt.</hi> I ſee many things out of order in Gods houſe, which doe perplexe me; eſpecially this, that they doe live of the alter, who doe not ſerve at the Altar; Church-locuſts, whoſe lips no lettice likes but ſacred <hi>Manna:</hi> and they in the the meane time that ſerve at the Alter, may ſtarve at the alter. I cannot here paſſe by the words of a Reverend Biſhop of this See;<note place="margin">D. King in his Lectures on Ionas.</note> Time was religion did eate up pollicie, and the Church devoured the commonwealth, but now pollicie eates up re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the Commonwealth devoures the Church. Men are profeſt Polititians; let the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth floriſh, and what care they for the Church? Now <hi>Munus offerendi</hi> is turned into <hi>Munus auferendi;</hi> and old <hi>Oblation</hi> is turned into <hi>Ablation.</hi> Our Gentiles (Heathens I had almoſt ſaid) doe breake into Gods houſe, and like bold theeves doe ranſacke and pillage it, and with more then heatheniſh petulancie trample underfoote the Miniſters of the Goſpel. We need not with that order of popiſh Prieſts, pul on ourſelves a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie beggery, for Gentlemen have enforced us to it of neceſſity. We may now ceaſe ſtudying of ſermons,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19758:18"/>
and ſtudy for bread to put in our mouthes: like the <hi>Iewes</hi> under the oppreſſion of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> when we ſhould make bricke, we are forced to gather ſtraw; when we ſhould worke in our vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, wee muſt looke out for ſuſtenance, wee muſt ſet our heads and our hands to worke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we muſt be Orators and Arators, Preachers and Plow-men, teachers and tent-makers: as if wee had the extraordinary diſpenſation of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching which S. <hi>Paul</hi> had, when he laboured with his hands and lived by his worke. <hi>Dionyſius</hi> tooke from an Image a golden covering, pretending that it was too hot for ſummer, and too cold for win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and gave one of wooll, ſaying, that that was fit both for ſummer and winter. So deale the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious perſons of this age, curſed Impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, corrupt Patrons, Barterers and purloyners of holy things, all thoſe that under pretence and colour of Law, cuſtome, compoſition, preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, doe cut ſhort the Miniſter of his proper portion; they take from the Miniſter his gold, which (ſay they) would make him proud, idle, covetous;<note place="margin">Cicero pro Roſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io Amarino.</note> and give him wooll, that will make him humble and laborious. Yet can they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (without pride ſure) weare gold on their ſpurres, who will not indure a Miniſter to have gold in his purſe. The Orator tells the grave Iudges and Senators in the Guild hall at <hi>Rome</hi> of a fellow called <hi>Fimbria,</hi> intolerably audacious, who ſtabbing <hi>Quintus Scaeuola</hi> at the funerals of <hi>Caius Marius,</hi> boaſted of the favour that he ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed unto him, <hi>Quòd non totum telum corpore ſuo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19758:18"/>
receperit,</hi> that he had not thruſt his dagger up to the hiles in his body. This fellow hath ſcattered his broode among us, there being too many that have beene ſpawned of him; who having ſeized upon a great part of the Churches Patrimonie, think it no ſmal kindnes they have ſhewd us, that they have not ſhred us of altogether, God is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to them for letting his houſe ſtand; though for the maintenance of his houſe and of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in his houſe, they have beene ſo bold with him, as either to ſhare halfe, or leave him none. Now as the Eagle in the Fable, that was ſhot fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ayre, did much lament, when ſhee ſaw her ſelfe to be ſhot with an arrow that was fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered with a plume of her owne wing: ſo may Religion mourne, when ſhee ſees her ſelfe thus wronged, by ſuch as will ſeeme moſt to bee of her owne ſide. They pretend purging, but intend pilling: they<note n="*" place="margin">D. Pridcaup ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on Rev. 2.4.</note> are ſweeping Gods houſe and prying into every corner, not to reſtore the groat that is loſt, but to take away the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that is left. To whom I may ſpeake in the words of <hi>Damaſus: Quâ fronte,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Damaſ Decre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.</note> 
               <hi>quâ conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entià oblationes vultis accipere?</hi> With what face or conſcience can yee receive tythes and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, that diſcharge no part of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall function in Gods houſe? You ſay, that they were taken from idle drones and fatte burſten-bellied Monkes and Fryers. But why are they now detained and kept backe from laborious &amp; painfull Paſtors? The founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19758:19"/>
are caſt downe: but <hi>what have the righteous done? Pſal.</hi> 11.3. The foundations of the Church which ſhould ſupport religion, tenths and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, are caſt downe, becauſe of ſuperſticious abuſers; but what have the righteous done, that theſe things ſhould be taken from them? but alas why ſhould I touch that ſore which is all dead fleſh? you may ſay to me, as on did to <hi>Luther,</hi> when he began to preach againſt the Popes Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie and tyrannie, you had as good hold your peace. This wickedneſſe is ſo powerfull that you will never be able to prevaile againſt it. Get you to your ſtudy, and ſay, Lord have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on us and procure your ſelfe no ill will. But be it good will, or be it ill will, wee come hither to ſpeake the truth: and for <hi>Sions</hi> ſake I will not hold my peace. Who knowes whether the Lord may be pleaſed to open the heart of one <hi>Lydia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 16.14.</note> to attend to the things which are ſpoken? Conſider then the danger of this ſinne: <hi>Prou.</hi> 20.25. It is a ſnare to a man to devoure holy things. As the feathers of an Eagle, laid with the feathers of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther birds, are ſaid to conſume them: ſo holy things, the goods of the Church, mingled with private mens patrimonies, do devoure them. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le parta, male dilabuntur:</hi> which may be obſerved by the Crane in Embleme, that having ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a wrongfull prey,<note place="margin">Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us Gelius N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tt. Alloc. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> could not digeſt it. When <hi>Scipio</hi> robbed the Temple of <hi>Tholoſſa,</hi> there was not a man that carried away any of the gold, who ever proſpered after it. That gold was not more fatall to the followers of <hi>Scipio,</hi> than the ſtollen
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19758:19"/>
goods of the Church have beene unfortunate to the Gentrie of our land. They have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved gangreenes to their whole eſtate, and as knot-graſſe to dogges, which being eaten keepes them from thriving: ſo that in the end theſe rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, or their poſterity prove beggers.<note place="margin">Aug. ad Mace<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don. Epiſt. 54. Dum. alienum rapis, a diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo raperis, et quamd in id de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, a diabolo detineris: reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes aurum, &amp; prodis coelum: iniuſte detines rem alienam, &amp; iuſte amittis haereditatem tu am: iniuſtum lucrum, ſed iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum damnum: lucrum in arca, ſed damnum in coſcicutia: per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat mundi lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum, per quod fit animae dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> But that's not the worſt: remember that of S. <hi>Auguſtine Multi in hac vita manducant quod poſtea apud in fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros digerunt</hi> Many devoure that in this life, which they ſhall digeſt in hell. And againe, <hi>Si in ignem mittitur, qui non dedit rem propriam, vbi mittendus qui in vaſit alienam? &amp;c.</hi> If hee bee decreed to the fire, which gave not his owne: whither is he to be ſent that hath robd another? whilſt thou ſnatcheſt from another, the Devill ſnatcheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thee: and ſo long as thou withholdeſt it, the Devill withholdeth thee: thou retaineſt gold, &amp; loſeth thine inheritance: an unjuſt gaine but a Iuſt loſſe. Lucre in thy coffer, but condemnation in thy conſcience: a miſcheife on that money that brings deſtruction to the ſoule. If this bee to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſe the portion and poſſeſſion of the Lord, if this be to rob the houſe of God, who dares lay ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious hands upon it? Oh meddle not with that which is conſecrated to God: as <hi>Pilates</hi> wife ſent her husband word, <hi>haue thou nothing to doe with that just man: Matth.</hi> 27.17. ſo, have thou nothing to doe with Gods portion: doe not forage his Church defraud his Miniſters, this is to rob God himſelfe. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Will a man rob God? yet ye have robbed me. But yee ſay, wherein have wee robbed thee, yee make your ſelves ignorant, as if yee
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19758:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
knew not that yee had robbed me in my tythes and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings. Yee are curſed with a curſe, for yee haue rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed me, even this whole nation: yee haue joined your ſelues in one to rob mee of my portion, thinking the commonneſſe of the offence to bee every mans particular juſtification therefore yee are heavily accurſed.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to terrifie thoſe ſacrilegious pioners of Gods houſe, that ſay with them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.12. <hi>Let us take to our ſelues the houſes of God in poſſeſſion.</hi> But I have ſpoken ſufficiently touching this kinde of violence, offered to the peculiar place of God. I paſſe now to another.</p>
            <p>Further, they are here to bee taxed, who carry themſelves irreverently in the place of Gods worſhip, which is the peculiar place of God, not a Barbers ſhop, nor an Apothecaries houſe, nor a common court, but the place of Angells and Archangels, the Kingdome of God, yea heaven it ſelfe<note n="*" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in 1 Cor. Hom. 36.</note>. Many by their indecent behaviour doe ſo vilifie this place, as if it were the worſt of all others, worſe then their owne houſes, as S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> complained in his time: for ther's or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der obſerved, but in the Church (ſaith he) is ſuch diſorder, ſuch confuſion, ſuch laughing, and ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and nodding, and whiſpering, ſuch a ſtirre and noiſe, that there is little or no difference made betweene the Church and an alehouſe; nay betweene the Church and a Play-houſe, nay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Church and a brothelhouſe, no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence made at all. I would to God this our irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence were not a juſt occaſion to the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts to ſcandalize our religion. S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19758:20"/>
24. exhorts us ſo to carrie our ſelves in the Church, that if an unbeleever come in, he may ſay, God is there, and God is in us, and may be drawne to joyne with us in the worſhip of God. But if ſuch a one ſhould come into ſome of our Congregations, and obſerve the carriage of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, he will well ſay, what Lord do this people ſerve, that are ſo irreverent? <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.10. The Lord ſaid to the Iewes in the like caſe, <hi>I have no pleaſure in you, neither will I accept an offering at your hand:</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 6. he tells them, that they deſpiſed his name and made his table contemptible. It is our ſinne at this day. Wee make his table con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, his throne contemptible, his houſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, his word contemptible, and all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, by our indecent behaviour in the place of his worſhip. Therefore I ſay in this caſe, as the Prophet did to them in the like,<note place="margin">Mal. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>I pray you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech God that he will be gracious unto us:</hi> Beſeech him with broken and bleeding hearts to be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious unto us in the pardoning of this ſinne.<note place="margin">Mac. 1.9. Mac. 2.3. Mac. 2.15.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how <hi>Antiochus</hi> was puniſhed for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning the houſe of God; ſo <hi>Heliodorus, Nicanor, Belſhazzar;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 5.</note> when Chriſt was in his humiliation he whipt out ſuch, ſhewing by that baſe puniſhment that they are not ſonns, but ſlaves: and will hee not then puniſh theſe now, being ſo highly exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? When King <hi>Ahaſhueroſh</hi> conceived that <hi>Haman</hi> would have forced Queene <hi>Ester,</hi> hee tooke it the worſe becauſe it was in his houſe,<note place="margin">Eſt. 7.8.</note> 
               <hi>Will he force the Queene before mee in the houſe?</hi> A man of the pooreſt condition cannot abide to ſee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19758:21"/>
his houſe abuſed: and ſhall God indure to ſee his abuſed? He cannot, he wil not: therfore beware of that. Let it ever be our care, when we enter in to the houſe of God, where Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt behold us, to doe nothing any way unbeſeeming that place.</p>
            <p>To conclude this point: If the place where God is worſhipt be his peculiar place, let us think upon the glory of this place, this land, I meane) this Kingdome wherein we live. Here is the place where God doth ſet his name, ſettle his worſhip and ordinances, as once he did in <hi>Shiloh,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward at Ieruſalem. Iſrael and England, though they lye in a divers climate, may bee ſaid right Parallels; not in Coſmographicall, but in Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall reſpects. Nay, we doe herein farre tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend them: they had onely a drop to refreſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, we have the whole ſtreames of Gods mercies poured upon us: they had only the green blade of corne, we have the plentifull increaſe as in the time of harveſt; they had the ſhadow, wee the ſubſtance; they had a glympſe of the Sunne, wee have him in the full ſtrength: they had the Paſchall lambe to expiate ſinnes typically; wee have the lambe of God to take them away really.<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.29. Gal. 4.</note> They were Alphabetarij and Abecedarij, young beginners, learning their A B C under the tutor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the law: but to us the Goſpel is give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in our ſaving health is ſpread before our belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving eyes, without any ſhadow caſt over the beau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty of it. We behold as in a mirrour the glory of the Lord with open face, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. we feed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19758:21"/>
the true Manna, and drinke of the water of life freely. Oh let us thankefully imbrace our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent happineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plato</hi> was thankefull to nature (as wee reade in <hi>Lactant.</hi>) 1. For that he was borne a man,<note place="margin">Lactant. l. 3 di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vin. Iuſt. c. 19</note> not a beaſt. 2. A man, not a woman. 3. A Greecian, not a Barbarian. 4. An Athenian, not a Theban; and finally, that he was borne in the time of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates.</hi> But much more thankefull ſhould wee be to the God of nature, for that we are borne, not Pagans, but Chriſtians; and in ſuch a place as England, where heaven ſtands open, which to other parts is barred on the outſide, with igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance or misbeliefe. England is the place of Gods worſhip, therefore the peculiar place of God; ſo that we may ſay, as it is in the <hi>Pſalme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 46.7.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord of hoſts is with us, the God of Iacob is our refuge:</hi> wee have his ſpeciall preſence, his ſpeciall protection, his ſpeciall bleſſing; and that ſo long as ever wee continue to ſerve him in holineſſe and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not one minute longer.<note place="margin">2. Obſervat.</note> For the holineſſe of the place cannot protect a people, except there be holineſſe in the perſons who inhabit that place: which is the ſecond point, that falls next into our conſideration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shiloh</hi> was a holy place, glorious for ſanctity and for the antiquity of that ſanctity: yet becauſe the inhabitants of it were not holy, both they and it were expoſed to the fury of the enemy.<note place="margin">Ioan. Papp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> in Ier. 7.12.</note> Though God in the old Teſtament would be worſhipped o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly in that place, where himſelfe had ſet the memory of his name: yet did hee not ſo tye the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19758:22"/>
memory of his name to any certaine place, but that fot the impiety of the people, he changed the place of his Tabernacle and Temple</p>
            <p>In the new Teſt. (becauſe the Goſpell was to be publiſhed through the whole world) that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of places is taken away; the time is now come, when neither in the mountaine of <hi>Samaria,</hi> nor yet at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 4.</note> men ſhall worſhip God by any ſuch tye. Now every place is ſo long (no longer) the Temple and habitation of God, as there ſhall be found in it true faith and holyneſſe of life. But where theſe ceaſe, where ſuperſtition and hereſie doe corrupt faith, and wickedneſſe ſucceeds in the roome of holineſſe,<note place="margin">Matt. 21.43.</note> there the like judgement is to be feared which befel <hi>Shiloh;</hi> that God will remove his kingdome of grace from ſuch a place or people, and give it to a Nation that will bring forth the fruites of it. <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> might goe to <hi>Shiloh,</hi> and <hi>England</hi> may goe to <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> to learne this leſſon, that the holineſſe of a place cannot protect a people, except &amp;c. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the City of the great King, the throne of God, the place of holy worſhip and perfit joy: tell her turrets and marke well her bulwarkes, carry in your mindes the Idaea of her gloryes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> de bello Iudaico. l. 7. ca. 7, 8, 9, 14, 17.</note> how ſhee was great among the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, princeſſe among the nations, the joy of the whole earth; and then on a ſodaine behold her Temple and houſes burning, the ſmoake of the fire waving in the ayre, and hiding the light of the ſunne, the flame riſing up to heaven, as if they would aſcend as high as their ſinnes had erſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19758:22"/>
done; her old and young, rich and poore, high and low, matrons, virgins, mothers, infants, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Prieſts, Prophets and Nazarites, fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, fettered, ſcattered, conſumed. Heer's a maiſter peece of Gods juſtice for ſinne: <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> once ſo glorious is now become a heap of ſtones, that holy citie, yea, that whole country is now become a ploughed field, layd waſt under the feete of Pagans; And the place of divine Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory become a den of Dragons.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ghieſler</hi> in <hi>Ier.</hi> 7.12.</note> Go from <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> to the Churches of <hi>Corinth, Galatia, Philippi, Epheſus, Smyrna, Nice, Laodicea, Antiochia,</hi> to all the Eaſterne and * African Churches, ſometime glorious Sanctuaries of the moſt high, conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his ſervice: when the inhabitants thereof became polluted, they were rejected of the Lord, who diſcarded their Idols and gave their land to be inhabited by <hi>Zijm</hi> and <hi>Ochim,</hi> Turkes and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels. The more gloriouſly the ſun and ſummer have apparrelled a tree, the more we admire the blaſting; but when God hath planted a people in his owne holy ground, (as he did <hi>Adam</hi> in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, Iſrael in <hi>Shiloh</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi>) watered it with the dewes of grace, ſhined on it with the beames of mercy, ſpent much care and coſt upon it; if this people brings forth no fruit or bad fruit, no marvaile, if there goes out a curſe, <hi>Never fruit grow on thee more;</hi> no marvaile; if God beſtow no more care nor coſt upon it, but ſuffers it to be laid waſt: as he ſometimes threatned to do to his Vineyard, <hi>Iſay</hi> 5.5. <hi>I will take away the hedge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I will breake downe the wall thereof, I will lay it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19758:23"/>
waſte.</hi> I, ſaith the Lord. For ſuch alterations and ſubverſions, are not to be aſcribed to fortune, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinie, ſtarrs, planets or the like, but to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, which is our next point.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Obſervat.</note>It is God who inflicts judgement upon a place, or people. <hi>See,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>what I did, Goe yee now &amp;c.</hi> It was he that forſooke the Tabernacle at <hi>Shiloh,</hi> he that delivered his ſtrength into capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, and his glory into the enemies hands: hee gave his people over unto the ſword, and was wroth with his inheritance, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.60.61. It was hee that gave the ſword a charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Aſhkelon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier 47 9 Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. Ier. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.25. Ier. 19.3.</note> that ſwept away the valiant men of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that opened his Armorie and brought forth weapons of indignation to ſmite <hi>Babilon;</hi> it is he that thus threatens <hi>Ieruſalem, Ièr.</hi> 18.11. <hi>I frame evill againſt you, and deviſe a deviſe againſt you.</hi> I will bring evill upon this place, the which whoſoever heareth, his eares ſhall tingle. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever calamities befall us, publique or private, they are from God: Hee is the Authour of all our Tragedies, and hath written out for us, and appoynted to us, the ſeverall parts, which we are to act in them.</p>
            <p>The more to blame then are thoſe impatient Spirits, that in the caſe of calamity are ſicke of the fret, not looking up to the hand of God, but fretting at the men and the meanes by which God doth afflict them: like the Ethiopians, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the Sunne, becauſe it ſcorcheth them with immoderate heate; or like curſt maſtives, that breake their teeth in gnawing thoſe iron chaines,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19758:23"/>
wherewith their Maſter ties them, and in biting the ſtaffe with which he beates them, as if a ſtaffe could ſmite, or a chaine bind, without an hand to uſe it It will be more laudable for us to imitate the Saints,<note place="margin">Pſal. 44.9. Iob 1.21. Chryſoſt. in 1. Ep. ad Theſſ.</note> who in every calamity did owne the hand of God. <hi>The Lord hath given,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob; the Lord hath taken away, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. What doeſt thou ſay, the Lord hath taken away? the theefe had taken away, the Sabeans had taken away his oxen, the Chaldeans had taken away his Camells: true, yet <hi>Iob</hi> complaines not of them, but lookes up to the hand of God. So ſhould wee in the like caſe. Doth the plague come? looke up to God: doth the ſword come? looke up to God: doth dearth come, poverty, ignominie, or any other calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Act it upon God.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 14 19.</note> As <hi>David</hi> inquired of the woman of <hi>Tekoah,</hi> if the hand of <hi>Ioab</hi> was not with her in the cloſe plea, and artificiall atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which ſhee made for <hi>Abſalom;</hi> in all our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes let us inquire, if there bee not the hand of God in them, and inquiring we ſhall finde it ſo: which when we have done, let us with patience reſigne up our ſelves into his hands, ſaying, (as the Church, <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.9.) <hi>I will beare the indignat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on of the Lord, becauſe I have ſinned againſt him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. Obſerv.</note> For it is our ſinne which kindleth the indignation of God, and provokes him to judgement, which is our next poynt. <hi>See what I did unto it for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of my people Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wickedneſſe was that cloud, in which all the ſtormes that fell on <hi>Shiloh</hi> were ingendred. It
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19758:24"/>
lyes in the power of ſinne and wickedneſſe, to make the moſt fruitfull land barren, and the moſt bleſſed place accurſed: A truth that may well paſſe for current, and being coyned in the mint of Gods word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.34. God turnes a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full land into barrenneſſe, for the wickedneſſe of the inhabitants that dwell therein,<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Civitatis ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio, morum, non murorum caſus.</hi> The ruine of a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is not ſo ſoone wrought by the weakneſſe of the walls, as by the lewdneſſe of their lives that are the inhabitants. Were the walls of a city ſtronger then thoſe of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the ſinnes within would hurle downe the walls without.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 13.9.</note> 
               <hi>Intra mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros hoſtis:</hi> thy perdition is of thy ſelfe ô Iſrael. The Heathen Hiſtorian<note n="*" place="margin">Abundant voluptates de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderium per lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xum atque libi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem pereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di perdendique omnia invexe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Liv. Heylin.</note> obſerved, that <hi>Rome</hi> began to looſe all, when ſinne abounded moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all, <hi>Romes</hi> vtter overthrowing was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but their vices abounding and ſinnes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflowing.</p>
            <p>An Engliſh Gentlemen at their expulſion out of <hi>France,</hi> was demanded by a French Cavalier when they would returne againe: his anſwer was feeling and pithie, When your ſinnes (quoth he) are greater than ours. He knew well that for ſins Kingdomes are tranſlated from one people to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and that a land ſpues out her inhabitants for the iniquity of them that dwell therein.<note n="*" place="margin">A. Gell. Noct. Attic. l. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</note> In <hi>A Gellius,</hi> mention is made of the horſe of <hi>Sejanus,</hi> called <hi>Sejus,</hi> this horſe, a goodly horſe to looke on, but whoſoever owned it, was ſtil unfortunate. Such a thing is ſinne, unfortunate to all: what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſover perſon or nation doth harbour it, can never
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19758:24"/>
proſper. S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> writes thus to <hi>Demetrian</hi> and others, who imputed to Chriſtian religion peſtilence, ſword, famine, and all the evills which then fell out in the world: Yee are diſcontented to ſee God diſpleaſed, yee are angry that God is thus angry, as if yee could deſerve from him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good by living ill, as if all theſe evills of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment were not leſſe than the evills of your ſinnes.<note n="*" place="margin">Hoſ. 2.14.</note> God of himſelfe is gracious, mercifull, ſlow to anger and of great kindneſſe, not willing to puniſh, except he be provoked: but if we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him by ſinne, we are ſure to feele the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. Looke into Paradiſe, looke into hell, looke into heaven, looke upon earth, and every where yee ſhall meete examples to confirme this.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Look into Paradiſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> where God placed our firſt parents, and inriched them with all ſorts of bleſſings; ſo ſoone as they fell into diſobedience and did eate of the forbidden fruit, they were caſt out: and as the ſentence was gone out of Gods mouth, ſo the ſword of juſtice,<note place="margin">2 Eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> followes to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute, they muſt die and all their poſterity. All muſt die in them, ſince all have ſinned in them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, looke into hell, ſee the unmerciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Dives</hi> puniſhed, according to the rule of juſtice. <hi>Deſideravit guttam, qui non dedit micam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Luk. 16.</note> He begg'd a drop of water and could not have it, becauſe he denied a crumme of bread before, when <hi>Lazarus</hi> begg'd it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.4.</note> Looke into heaven and ſee ſinne pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19758:25"/>
there: God ſpared not the Angels that ſinned, not thoſe glorious inhabitants of heaven, but caſt them downe to hell. And art thou bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or dearer than the Angels?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, looke upon earth, and ſee there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable puniſhments, both perſonall and nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall, inflicted for ſinne. Every ſtory is a Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle of this truth, and the whole world but the practiſe.<note place="margin">Gen. 7.11.</note> For ſinne God ſluced out flouds from the ſea and opened the windowes of heaven, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the retentive power from the clouds, that they might powre downe unmeaſurably to drowne the old world; for ſinne he rained down fire from heaven to conſume <hi>Sodom,</hi> and opened the jawes of the earth to ſwallow <hi>Corah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 16.31.</note> for ſin he ſent Ieruſalem into captivity,<note place="margin">Ier. 40.2. Ier. 33.15. Ier. 30.15.</note> and ſuffered <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loh</hi> to be msde deſolate, <hi>Goe yee now, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>See what I did unto it:</hi> conſider how I deprived it of my mercies, and made it a ſpectacle of my juſtice. So true is that, <hi>Ier.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Evill ſhall come upon ſinners.</hi> The evill of ſinne, is but an earneſt laid downe for the evill of puniſhment. If ſinne be the herald going before, puniſhment will bee the attendant, and follow after. When diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hath playd her part, then vengeance comes upon the ſtage. Should I turne over every leafe of ſacred writ, and ſearch all Fathers, and all wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters divine and humane, by innumerable teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, I ſhould evince this truth, that ſinne hales on puniſhment. It is ſo ſure a concomitant of ſinne, that oftentimes the word which ſignifies ſinne, is tranſlated puniſhment<note n="*" place="margin">Zach. 14.19</note>: as if ſinne and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19758:25"/>
were <hi>termini convertibiles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Raro antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentem ſcele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum Deſcruit pede poena claudo.</note> in a manner all one. Haply it is ſometimes puniſhed ſlowly, but alwayes ſurely. For a while it may with a bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned face out brave vertue, and ſo flouriſh as if vice were the onely favourite of heaven: but, if wee have time for obſervation, we ſhall ſee it halting on a crutch, and bluſhing for ſhame. It winds a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout men, like a ſubtile river, (ſeeming onely to runne on his courſe) doth yet ſearch as it runnes, gliding ſo ſlily by, as if it ſcarcely toucht the bank, yet ſtil eats ſomething in it.<note n="*" place="margin">Plut. de ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> numinis ultio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. Iſiodor Peleuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot lib. 1. Epiſt. 6.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Gods juſtice is like a mill: it may be late, ere it doth grinde a man for ſinne, but when once it begins to doe it, it grinds him to powder. <hi>On whomſoever this ſtone ſhall fall, it will grind him to powder</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 21.44.</note>. Gods patience being abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, is turned into fury; and then <hi>horrendum eſt, &amp;c. It is a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the loving God: Heb.</hi> 10.31. <hi>Aquinas</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Aquin. ſum. p. 3. q. 86. art. 4.</note> (not amiſſe) gives this reaſon why men muſt be puniſhed for ſinne: The diſorder of ſinne (ſaith hee) cannot be reduced to the order of juſtice, but by puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for it is juſt that he, who, more than hee ought, hath followed his will, ſhould ſuffer ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt his will. This may bee the way to reforme him to Gods will. Though the anvile being beaten upon doth waxe harder, yet being put into the fire it becomes ſoft: ſo ſinners may be ſoftned by puniſhment, that are hardned by mercies.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if God ſhould never puniſh ſinne, wicked men would thinke God altogether like
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19758:26"/>
themſelvs, &amp; conclude him a pertaker in their ſins <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.21. An ill tempered body, the more it is fed with good nouriſhment, the worſe it is: ſo an ill tempered ſoule, with the untempered mortar of ſinne, becomes worſe for the mercy and lenity of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if God ſhould never puniſh ſinne, wicked men would ſet at nought al his miniſters, and conclude them falſe Prophets in denouncing judgements that never come upon them. <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.12,<note place="margin">S Chryſoſtome in Epiſt. ad Rom Hom 25.</note> 13, 14. Therefore (ſaith <hi>Chryſostome</hi>) doth God puniſh many in this world, that becauſe they will not believe (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) the words of commination, they may believe (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) the deeds of execution.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, when ſinne is ripened, God is much provoked, and it is then an eaſing of him to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſinne. <hi>Ah, I will eaſe me of mine adverſaries and avenge me on mine enemies, Iſay</hi> 1.24. Till he is thus eaſed, he is by our ſinnes preſſed under us, as a cart that is full of ſheaves, <hi>Amos</hi> 2.13. Our ſinnes diſturbe God in the higheſt heaven, they cry unto him for vengeance, as the ſinnes of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> did, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. And if our ſinnes cry, ſhall not he (that made the eare) heare? juſtice is his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and it is a righteous thing with him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe ſinne with puniſhment, 2 <hi>Theſſ</hi> 1.6. Vpon thoſe words of the Lord, (<hi>Ier</hi> 4.3, 4. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w not among thornes, lest my fury come forth like fire, and burne that none can quench it, becauſe of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of your doings:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ghiſt. in loc.</note>) It is obſerved by ſome, that ſinnes are as thornes, which doe eaſily kindle
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19758:26"/>
the fire of Gods wrath. His wrath<note n="*" place="margin">Id. in Ier. 15.14.</note> is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as a fire covered with embers; his divine love, I meane, (which is as warme embers) doth cover his wrath: but our ſinnes, as a violent wind, doe blow away thoſe embers; and then his wrath appeares, then his fury breakes forth like fire, and burnes that none can quench it.</p>
            <p>I want time to handle the laſt obſervation, therefore joyntly to apply this with the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent points: Yee have heard, firſt, that it is God, who inflicts judgement. Secondly, that he doth it not except he be provoked by wickedneſſe; and if he be ſo provoked, hee will doe it. Thirdly, and that to his owne place and people.</p>
            <p>Behold here how wee may come to loſe all our prerogatives, Churches, Cities, proſperity,<note place="margin">Application.</note> ſafety, peace, Goſpell, and what not? by running the courſes of wickedneſſe. Who can number the bleſſings we have enjoyed? The world can tell that of all the trees in the garden wee are the Vine; amongſt all flowers, wee are the lillie;<note place="margin">2 Eſdr. 5.23</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all fowles, we are the dove; amongſt all cities, wee have <hi>Shiloh</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> Vpon us God hath with a full hand powred thoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, which he hath but ſprinkled upon others: temporall, I meane, as well as ſpirituall bleſſings. All other countries are in ſome things defective;<note place="margin">Sands Trav. l. 4.</note> but England, like a provident parent, doth mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter unto us whatſoever is uſefull; foraigne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions but onely tending to vanity and luxury. The ſummer burnes us not, nor doth the winter benumme us. Wee may ſit and ſing under our
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19758:27"/>
owne fig-trees,<note place="margin">—Penitus to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to diviſos orbe Britannos. <hi>Vir.</hi>
               </note> and drinke the wine of our owne vineyeards. As in ſituation, ſo in felicity, our beloved Iſle is wholly diſioyned from all the world. They that have travelled the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke Provinces, can witneſſe the miſerable foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of warre,<note place="margin">Eccl. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and the tyrannie of deſolation: Churches and Cities have no more monuments, but the ruined foundations, to teſtifie that they were. Whereas peace is within our wals, and proſperity within our Palaces. Our artificers may ſing in their ſhops, husbandmen may cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully follow the plough, and ſtudents peaceably apply their bookes. We heare not the murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring pieces about our eares, we ſee not our Churches &amp; houſes flaming over our heads; we feare not rapes and outragious violences to be offered to our wives, our daughters, our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trones, and our virgins. We feele not the rifling of our houſes, the ranſacking of our temples, the ſpoyling of our goods, nor the miſerable inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of our inſulting enemies. We ſee not the wife breathing out her life in the armes of her husband; nor the tender babe, ſnatcht from the mothers breaſts, either bleeding dead on the paveme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or ſprawling on the merciles pikes. We ſee not the high way ſtrewed with breathleſſe carkaſſes, nor our ſtreets ſwimming with blood. We cannot judge of the terrors of warre, but by report and heare-ſay. Though God hath toſſed our neighbour-nations, and made them like a wheele, and as the ſtubble before the winde; yet this Iland, or Britaine, our deare Country, hath
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19758:27"/>
ſtood like the Center, with unmooved firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Oh how happy might we be, if our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity did not envie our proſperity, nor our wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe make way to our wretchedneſſe? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it come to paſſe, <hi>Ex Daemonis injuria,</hi> vel <hi>Ex hominis incuria,</hi> from the Divels malice, or mans neglect, ſo it is, that for ſo many talents of Gods bleſſings, we give him not a dramme of ſervice. Nay, we give him the worſt of all things, who hath given us the beſt of all things. For his bleſſings heapen, and ſhaken, and thruſt together, we give him iniquities preſſed downe, and yet running over. As <hi>Archimedes</hi> tombe was over-growne with thornes,<note place="margin">Cic. Tuſculan. quaeſt. lib. 5.</note> when <hi>Cicero</hi> came to viſit it: ſo is our land with heapes of vices. From the Cedar to the ſhrubbe, from the Eagle to the wren, from the higheſt to the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, from the yongeſt to the oldeſt; we have all corrupted our wayes. Sin was woont to love privacy, as if ſhe walked in feare, like one in danger of an Arreſt: but now ſhe dares ſhew her face without bluſhing. Though the heavens bluſh at the view, and the earth ſweat at the burden of ſo vile ſinners, and the Prophets proclaime open ſhame and confuſion againſt them: yet they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhrinke at the ſhame, nor feele the horror, nor feare the revenge. Now may we ſee the truth of that Praemonition,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.1.</note> In the laſt dayes perillous times ſhall come. The times are now ſo perillous, that it is ſcarce ſafe to be an honeſt man. Vertue, like <hi>Ioſeph</hi> for his goodneſſe, is brought to the ſtockes and yrons. Looke upon
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19758:28"/>
this Angle of the world; for ſo, we thinke <hi>ANGLIA</hi> ſignifies: how doth it ſwarme with all abominations? with oppreſſion, extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, prophanenes, uncleannes, unmercifulneſſe, envie, malice, pride, fraude, briberie, luxurie, and the reſt? for to name all particulars is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. We neede rather teares to bewaile them than a tongue to report them. And, if the whole land be ſo full of ſin, ſhall we thinke this City free? Nay, this is the Pontificall ſeat of ſinne, where ſhe is never non-reſident. As many lines meet at the Center: ſo all ſins by a generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence to this place.<note n="*" place="margin">Holinſhed Chron. Ann. 1. of Q. Mary. Grimſtone State of the Empire. p. 566</note> The word of <hi>Stephen Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner, L.</hi> Chancelor, to Sr. <hi>Thomas White,</hi> L. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor in the ſtar Chamber. <hi>My L. take heed to your charge, the Citie of</hi> London <hi>is a whirlpoole, and a ſinke of evill rumors, there they be bred, and from thence ſpread into all parts of this Realme.</hi> There is a commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Proverbe in Germany, that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of Suabe alone is able to furniſh all Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many with ſtrumpets, Franconia with rogues and beggers, Bohemia with heretickes, Bavaria with theeves, Weſtphalia with perjurers and falſe witneſſes, and the Marquiſat of the Rhine with gluttons. I would to God, that <hi>London</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone could not furniſh all England with all theſe; with ſtrumpets, rogues, beggers, heretickes, theeves, falſe witneſſes, gluttons; and with any others, that are audacious in ſinne. Our wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe is ſuch, and ſo much, that it is all, if the idolatry of Rome, or the blaſphemy of Turkey, can go beyond it.<note place="margin">Rev. 3.1.</note> I know there are a few names
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19758:28"/>
in <hi>Sardis, that have not defiled their garments;</hi> ſome amongſt us, that make conſcience of their waies: but what are theſe in compariſon of the reſt? How many ignorant are there, to one that hath ſound knowledge? how many ſwearers, to one that feares an oath? how many oppreſſors, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers and hypocrites to one truly religious? As <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> juſtified <hi>Sodom,</hi> ſo we may well juſtifie <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> abounding in all damnable abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>What then can we expect but that God ſhould ſtint the influence of his favour toward us, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from us all his bleſſings, powre upon us the full vials of his wrath, and make us a ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of his juſtice, as he did <hi>Shiloh</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee are now by reaſon our ſinnes, circled round with imminent dangers, deſtruction with ſaile-ſtretcht wings hovers o're our heads, and a cloud of miſchiefe is ready to breake upon us. Not to mention other particulars, materiall in this kind, the glory of our nation hath of late bin eclypſed, the lively luſtre whereof was ere while ſo reſplendent, that it dazled the eyes of all ſuch as were neere or about us; God hath not gone out with our armies, but hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred our enemies to prevaile; our young men and our ſtrong men of the higheſt ranke have fallen by the ſword. So that, as fluttering birds fly wondering about the Owle, our friends have wondred, our foes rejoiced at our ill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe; hiſſing and clapping their hands, to ſee our glory ſwallowed up. Whence this but from
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19758:29"/>
our ſinnes<note n="*" place="margin">Indeed wee doe commonly impute it unto other cauſes, but wee forget our ſinnes, which are the principall.</note>?</p>
            <p>Beſides, the maſſacring Angell, that harbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of death, doth againe viſite our land; God for our ſinnes doth now ſend the peſtilence home to our dores, this his purſevant rides cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit in our City, Country, and Vniverſity; and catcheth men as with a ſnare, perhaps when they moſt haſt from him, and will not be rid away, ſo long as our ſinnes invite him to tarty. Our ſins are the cart-ropes that hale downe the plague and all other judgements upon us; they are the enemies that ring our knelles and proclaime our funerals; they are the thicke clouds which hinder the Sun-ſhine of our proſperity; they are the falſe ſtrumpets that make a divorce between Gods mercy and our ſafety; they are the trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors that forfeit into Gods hands all thoſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, which we have hitherto injoied. And ſhal we ſtill twiſt theſe cart-ropes and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the hands of theſe enemies? ſhall wee ſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe theſe clouds, and foſter theſe ſtrumpets and traitors? Nay, rather let us bethink our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves of ſome remedy againſt that miſery which is like to fall upon us. <hi>ENGLAND</hi> hath now for her ſinnes (as it were) many ſwords drawne out againſt her, and ſhal ſhe provide no buckler? Her owne brood is ready to bite out her belly, to put out her candle, to ſhake her foundations, and ſhall we not looke about us?</p>
            <p>Where are you, yee deputies of <hi>Moſes,</hi> yee ſonnes of the Higheſt, into whoſe hands God hath put a ſword of authority, for no other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19758:29"/>
but to ſtrike at ſinne? Will yee ſuffer it to ruſt in the ſheath, or hold it in your hand and never ſtrike? Will yee, like <hi>Iehojakim,</hi> ſit beaking your ſelves before the fire of eaſe and reſt, and wholly neglect the diſcharge of that high place to which God hath called you? Or will yee for a bribe ſell your connivence (and withall your conſcience) where yee ſhould give your puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhment?<note place="margin">Hoſ. 5.7. &amp; 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 12.</note> Will yee <hi>turne righteouſnes into worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, judgement into gall, and the fruit of right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe into hemlocke?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Miſtake me not, I aime at no particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and I truſt you will not condemne the poore ſwallowes for chattering and uſing their voice, agreably to nature. <hi>Beſſus</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Plut. de ſera numinis ultio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</note> ſurmiſed they cried againſt him, that he had kil'd his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If the ſpeech meet with any of you in particular, it is not in my intent, but in the event. Nor do I lay the fault upon Magiſtrats in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, that all ſorts of ſinnes are ſo riſe amongſt us. Yet (to ſpeake truth) when I conſider how powerfully the Miniſters of this land, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they of this City, do labour to beate downe ſinne, I begin to thinke there is ſome want of courage or diligence in the Magiſtrate: &amp; that he himſelfe is perſuaded, that if hee would doe his beſt, many diſorders might be repreſſed. The unhappy <hi>Cynicke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diogenes.</note> when he ſaw the boy play the idle packe, went and beat his maſter. So when we ſee the forenamed ſinnes fly about, as fiery ſerpents, we muſt blame the Magiſtrate, and ſay with the Prophet,<note place="margin">Pſal. 58.1</note> 
               <hi>Is it true? do yee judge the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19758:30"/>
thing that is right and execute with an upright hart?</hi> Do not our lawes ſtrike at many diſorders that are common amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt us? Have we no law againſt raſh ſwearing? God bee thanked, we have: but wher's the execution? Have we no law againſt Sabbath breaking? yes againſt that too. Yet is it openly prophaned. The reformation of theſe two (to omit many others) I would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to this Honorable Bench, but that mee thinkes I heare my friends telling me, what <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolet</hi> ſaid to <hi>Eraſmus. Eraſmus</hi> would proove that worſhipping of images might well be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed. <hi>I grant</hi> (quoth <hi>Sadolet) thy opinion is good: but this ſhould not be handled becauſe it will not bee granted.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir Francis Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con Apotheg. 29.</note> When <hi>Lycurgus</hi> was to reforme and alter the ſtate of <hi>Sparta,</hi> in the conſultation, one adviſed, that it ſhould be reduced to an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute popular equality. But <hi>Lycurgus</hi> ſaid to him; Sir, begin it in your owne houſe. If the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate would begin to reforme things amiſſe in his owne houſe, there were hope of amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It is not my practiſe to ſcan Magiſtrates, nor to rake into their actions: but this I have heard from ſome of your owne Bench, that by reaſon of your ſolemne meetings, and feaſtings this day at the houſe of the Magiſtrate, the day is ſcarcely ſo well ſanctified there as it ought to be. I know not whether it be ſo or not, let them looke to it whom it doth concerne. Howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the counſell of a reverend Biſhop of our Church,<note place="margin">Babington on exod. c. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in ſuch a caſe, is not to be miſliked. <hi>So ought we to dreſſe meate upon holy dayes, that ever
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19758:30"/>
we have a care of the ſalvation of them that dreſſe it:</hi> who being created and redeemed as we our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves be, ought not ſo evermore to be kept at this ſervice, as that never they may heare the word, receive the Sacrament, and praiſe God in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation with his people. For that ſhould bee to eate the fleſh of them, and to drinke the blood of them moſt cruelly, yea, to bury them in our bellies:<note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.16.</note> and for our bodies to deſtroy their ſouls for ever. Rather remember <hi>Davids</hi> refuſall to drinke the water that was bought ſo deare; and provide ſo that the one being done, the other may not be left undone. I know well, that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats are called Gods, becauſe they repreſent his Majeſty and magnificence on earth, in which reſpect much is to be granted them: but yet (by your leave) ſuch ſhould remember, that the neerer they are to heaven in greatneſſe, the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer they ſhould be unto it in goodneſſe; that as God hath honored them, ſo they ſhould honor him. I take not upon me to preſcribe in this caſe, yet me thinkes ſome other day as well as this, might ſerve the turne for ſolemne feaſts, if cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome were not more prevalent than conſcience.<note n="*" place="margin">Magis nos docere debet judicium veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iudicium con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudinis. Aug. in pſal. 105,</note> Therefore among your manifold conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I beſeech you to thinke upon the redreſſe of this, and withall of the publicque and groſſe prophanation of this day.</p>
            <p>But I muſt crave pardon, for I feare that through prolixity I have tranſgreſſed, whilſt the zeale of Gods glory hath inlarged my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe againſt the tranſgreſſions of the time.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:19758:31"/>Yet may I with leave ſtraine my diſcourſe one pegge higher: and I will promiſe not to be over-bold with your patience.</p>
            <p>There is a ſinne, too much practiſed in this City,<note place="margin">Deut. 25.15, Pro. 11.1.</note> which (the Scripture ſaith) <hi>is an abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Lord;</hi> and it ſhould be ſo to his Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, the Magiſtrate. I meane fraud, in ſelling by falſe balance, unjuſts weights and meaſures; and in cunning conveyances, in weighing or meating; ſuch as cheat the buyer. They ſay, there are ſom who in ſtead of <hi>Troy</hi> weights uſe <hi>Venice</hi> weights, which are very deceitful &amp; not warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by law:<note place="margin">Silk-men.</note> they ſay, that amongſt * <hi>Grocers, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, Colemeaters, Victuallers</hi> and divers others, there is much fraud uſed in this kind and to the great detriment of his majeſties ſubjects. I am not a ſhamed to name theſe things in this place, when they require reformation. There are laws (no doubt) enacted againſt this injuſtice: but theſe laws without execution are but a dead let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. It is in you (Right Honorable) to put life into theſe laws, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> did into the <hi>Shunamites</hi> ſonne, and to ſet them upon their feet: it is in you, to take away theſe exactions from Gods people, and to maintaine the true weight and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance. There is another diſorder, which had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſlipt my memory; they ſay, that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, which the Country brings in to ſerve the City, cannot be bought by houſholders but at a deere rate and at the ſecond hand; the hands (I meane) of regrators and huckſters that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall the market. Shall theſe things paſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controlled,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19758:31"/>
unpuniſhed, unreformed? God forbid. The mentioning of theſe particulars, ſome may thinke not ſo fit in a ſermon. But the care is taken, let them thinke what they pleaſe; I am ſure this exaction and injuſtice doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe God. The poore people already ſmart for it, and (if it be not puniſhed) the whole land may ſmart for it. No queſtion, you know many other particulars, in this, and other kinds, which require ſpeedy reformation: therefore ſet your ſelves to the worke. Let it be your care (Right Honorable) to puniſh theſe and all others ſinnes: doe ſomething this yeere, that may cauſe you to be had in remembrance hereafter. Be not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull to your Country, whilſt you are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-mercifull to offenders, but puniſh offenders and ſtrike at the root of ſin, for ſinne ſtriketh at the root, &amp; ſhaketh the foundation of our land.</p>
            <p>In briefe, let inferiours as well as ſuperiours, every one in his ſeverall place put his hand to this worke. Every one that loves his nation, that favours religion, that wiſheth the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Goſpell, deſires ſpeace and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity unto our kingdom, let him co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrat his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to pull down the kingdome of ſin. Downe wih it, downe with it, even to the ground. So long as ſinne reigneth, our kingdome cannot flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: but the ſinewes of our ſtate will ſhrinke, our policy will be no better than lunacy, and our glory bee turned into ignominy. It is not our profeſſion of the Goſpel, nor any other prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, that can in this caſe defend us. Did not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19758:32"/>
God puniſh <hi>Shiloh</hi> his owne place: and Iſrael his owne people? Did hee not permit the <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans</hi> to deſtroy the Temple built by <hi>Salomon;</hi> the <hi>Romans</hi> to overthrow the ſecond Temple; the <hi>Turks</hi> to overthrow the Chriſtian Churches in <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Europe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir Walter Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh Hiſt. of the world l. 2. c. 15 § 1.</note> when the people became wicked? The <hi>Trojans</hi> beleeved, that while their <hi>Palladium,</hi> or the Image of <hi>Minerva,</hi> was kept in <hi>Troy,</hi> the City ſhould never bee overturned; the <hi>Christians</hi> in the laſt fatall battell againſt <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladine</hi> did carry into the field, as they were made beleeve, the very croſſe wheron Chriſt died, and yet they loſt the battell, their bodies, and the wood: as the Iſraelites did the Arke, when they fetched it into the camp, from <hi>Shiloh.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore truſt not to the ſigne, but to the ſubſtance of Gods worſhip; it is not the profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of religion,<note place="margin">Eccl. 7.10.</note> that can gard us. Look we ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to that, and this wee cannot doe, except we abandon our ſinnes. Therefore abandon your ſinnes, caſt away from you all your tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions whereby yee have tranſgreſſed, pull thoſe Scorpions out of your boſomes, weed theſe nettles out of the garden of your hearts, ſpue out this gall of bitterneſſe, break off theſe bonds of iniquity. Say not thou (if thou wouldeſt chop Logicke with God) what is the cauſe that the former dayes were better than theſe? <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrastus</hi> makes it the character of a pratler,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophraſt. Charact. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to find fault with the preſent times, and to ſay men are now worſe than before. We all cry out, the dayes are evill, while wee helpe to make them
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19758:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
worſe. All complaine all cenſure, none amend. The Scribe points to the Publican, the proud gallant points to the miſerable churle; the well conceited hypocrite blames the diſſolute, &amp; the diſſolute layes the fault on the hypocrite, that the dayes are evill. But if every one would mend one, the times would then be better. Therefore let every one begin at home. It was the proud Phariſee that broke his neighbours head, the poore Publican ſmote his owne boſome.<note place="margin">Luk. 18.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude all: God hath highly advanced us into his favour, he hath honored this nation of ours above all the nations in the world; for ſhame let not us out-ſinne all the nations in the world; for, if we out-act them in ſinne, we muſt out-ſuffer them in puniſhment. For our ſins paſt let us ſeriouſly humble our ſelves, and by faith lay hold on Chriſt, that they may be pardoned: and for time to come let vs implore the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Gods Spirit, that we may be able by his power to mortifie our ſinnes. So ſhall that cloud of judgement be diſſolved, which hangs over our heads; ſo ſhall that fire of wrath bee quenched, which is already kindled, ſo ſhall that ſword of vengeance be put againe into his ſheath which is already drawne out, but hath not ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken home, ſo ſhall Gods bleſſings fall downe upon us, like gracious ſhowers; ſpirituall, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, eternall bleſſings; perſonall and nationall bleſſings; whole miriads of bleſſings. Happy, ô happy, are the people that are in ſuch a caſe: bleſſed, ò bleſſed is that people, that have the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19758:33"/>
Lord for their God. This bleſſedneſſe we begge at thy hands ô bleſſed Father, and that for the ſake of our bleſſed Saviour Ieſus Chriſt, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with thine owne Majeſty and bleſſed Spirit, bee aſcribed all honor and glory, now and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19758:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
